[SPEAKER_00]: And how many times a day you eat it helps to answer his question?
[SPEAKER_04]: It helps that self-control.
[SPEAKER_04]: So it's, you know, if you eat when you're hungry for the purpose of hunger,
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, it will be easier for you to catch your mind when you want to eat for the purpose of pleasure, or distraction, or because you're bored, or because you saw some nice food that you wanted always to eat, but you're not really hungry.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, all of those things means you're giving in to the pointless desires that are not really necessary, which means that's how your mind will control you then.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, eh... people don't eh... don't want to think about it when things are pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because then, what you give in, you get rewarded with pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: But because giving in to such pointless desires, as I said, keeps your mind not tame, let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, when you experience discomfort, when that same untamed mind starts to resist and rebel and shout, you also can't calm it down, because you've been just
[SPEAKER_04]: Like feeding a dog treats all the time and not teaching it any discipline.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, when that dog gets upset, he won't listen to you when you tell him to shut up or sit quietly, because you haven't trained it when you could.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's important to recognize that it's not just about sort of overcoming pain and suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: It is, but through also self-control and sensory strain in regard to pleasures that usually intoxicate the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's that self-control that comes through precepts and sensory strain.
[SPEAKER_07]: After you gain this self-control, then, do you still seek pleasures?
[SPEAKER_07]: Or, if you don't seek it, can you have it without being attached to it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Depends.
[SPEAKER_04]: Depends what pleasures.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, pleasures of food or, I don't know, pleasant sights.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can have it without being attached.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, like, sexual pleasures,
[SPEAKER_04]: Pleasures of a more intoxicating natures, you can't have those without being attached to them.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's either or.
[SPEAKER_04]: You either give them up or you're still attached to them.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't have them and be free from them at the same time.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you understand the nature of suffering and how to achieve freedom from suffering, when you are talking to some friend or relative,
[SPEAKER_05]: You can see that the person doesn't have this awareness of suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: How can you help other people in achieving the awareness?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you can help someone only if they want to be helped.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you can't make them aware if they don't want to hear it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if they want to hear it, then you don't really need my advice on how to help them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just tell them exactly what you just said.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I think the problem is that they don't want to be helped, but you want to help them still.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, try perhaps, you know, hinting that they should reconsider whether they need help or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, eh... sometimes if you come, like, head-on trying to give them what helped you, will help you as well, people will reject it, and they'll not respect it as much, because they feel like you're putting it onto them.
[SPEAKER_05]: But sometimes they... they know... they want to
[SPEAKER_05]: Do they know they're supposed to look inside?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, you can only give them right information, but if they don't follow it, means they just say they want to understand, but they're obviously not doing everything about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Everybody wants to be free from suffering, but that doesn't mean that everybody will make the effort to train themselves to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_08]: How do you train yourself?
[SPEAKER_04]: As I just described, taking on the precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Precepts?
[SPEAKER_04]: The rules of behavior.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, don't do unwholesome things by body, speech, mind, sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't just go to pleasures blindly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, moderate in eating, exactly, finding the right reasons for consuming food, mindfulness, watchfulness of your intentions, everything the suttas talk about.
[SPEAKER_06]: And also, probably, just, you know, this recognition of there are situations where the other side
[SPEAKER_06]: Other... either cannot, at this particular point, accept any type of help, or they're not really willing.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, they might be asking questions like, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_06]: But whenever you provide some sort of suggestion, they are just kind of...
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's... that's when you're gonna see whether they want help or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: When people ask you, tell them what to do, and they don't do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not it's not your issue, but then you realize, okay, so they're not really asking.
[SPEAKER_04]: They're asking just in order to hear what they want to hear.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you tell them what they don't want to hear, they're not going to do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Everybody has their choices.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if they come and ask, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_04]: What did the Buddha teach?
[SPEAKER_04]: What is the practice?
[SPEAKER_04]: You tell them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Tell them clearly.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is what it is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Take it or leave it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Basically, that's all that's all the Buddha could have done.
[SPEAKER_04]: He often said, you know, I would present it, and sometimes a person would follow it, and yeah, that's pleasing, because I didn't waste my time.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sometimes I would present the teaching, person would go and do the opposite thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's displeasing, because I've wasted my time.
[SPEAKER_04]: But either way, my mind is not bothered by it, because it's not... it's not his responsibility, really.
[SPEAKER_06]: Maybe just a very short follow-up question on this.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sometimes, when I find myself in this particular situation, I wonder,
[SPEAKER_06]: Whether it's, you know, whether it is the issue that the other person doesn't really want to hear, or whether I have not been able to find a way to communicate something that would sound meaningful to the other person.
[SPEAKER_06]: And what I mean by that is, for instance, all this, all these different ways that the Buddha uses to convey his message.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure, there's a skill in teaching, in recognizing what's valuable, but that is secondary, really.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, sometimes people get burdened by this pressure to help and convey, you know, that this you must help you, but that is secondary, really.
[SPEAKER_04]: What you must do is not lose perspective and act out of that pressure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, you will be the most accurate in whatever you say.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you start really acting out of that compulsion to help them, you are losing your perspective.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if you're just parroting the teaching, it's still... you're doing it now out of that emotional need to satisfy your own desire of being heard and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you just have to recognize.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because sometimes it's better to not say everything, than to give too much information as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you won't see that if you're if you're gripped by that.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I must help.
[SPEAKER_04]: I must help.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I also have a question on these connections.
[SPEAKER_03]: I already asked you in privately about this, so... but maybe some more information could be helpful.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the Buddha himself, so he sometimes was asked by just people, people I say like this, like just those who want to live
[SPEAKER_03]: happily at home with their wives and sons.
[SPEAKER_03]: And basically, he was telling them, you need to keep five precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, yeah, I wonder, well, they obviously believed in afterlife.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, yeah, for them it was meaningful.
[SPEAKER_03]: But do you think that, like, for people nowadays, who also just want to have this, say, worldly happiness, well, it makes any sense to speak about
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_04]: As I said in that... few Zooms ago we did, again, the mind is happy or unhappy, not because of the world, not because of what's happening in the world, but because whether the mind is trained or tamed, or how much it's trained or tamed.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, in other words, you can have everything bad happen around you, but if your mind is trained and calm, you will not be unhappy on account of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I think, deep down, even the most unrestrained person values the idea, at least, of a peaceful mind, of mind that's not disturbed by things.
[SPEAKER_04]: He just doesn't know how to go about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, five precepts is how you go about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, even if you don't believe in what the Buddha said, or any other religion, and you're just a pure scientist, and you don't care about the future lives, you do know the value of peace, here and now, and it's not going to come through a mild behavior.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's obvious to a ten-year-old boy, who knows.
[SPEAKER_04]: He doesn't want to do anything about it, but he knows that he needs to calm down when the parents tell him to.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, eh... so, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you just mention the five precepts for those who don't know?
[SPEAKER_04]: The Five Precepts are not killing, not stealing, not lying, not cheating or engaging in, like, extreme levels of sensuality and not drinking or taking drugs and intoxicants that will pollute your mindfulness and awareness of day-to-day life.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, within that, you can practice, then, the refined precepts of speech.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, don't talk unless you have something to say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't insult people, gossip, spread rumors, chit-chat.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just, again, like...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, first, it's the physical behavior.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, you hone in the verbal behavior.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, it's just a training.
[SPEAKER_04]: The Buddha would often compare, like, training a wild elephant.
[SPEAKER_04]: You get him from the wilderness, tie him down until he calms down.
[SPEAKER_04]: When he calms down, offer him food.
[SPEAKER_04]: If he doesn't take the food, then keep him tight, then offer him, then he takes the food out, then he's ready to listen, and that's how you develop the training.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's the same principle, really.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but in this connection, like, so people would generally, I say, agree, let's say, normal situation, it's good to follow these rules, it makes sense, but let's say, yeah, like, for the war, I would ask you, like, the situation that we are now in.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, people would say, yeah, I mean, it's not good to kill in principle, but yeah, but I cannot, let's say, lose everything.
[SPEAKER_04]: So... Well, you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Either you defend and kill, or... and break the precepts, or you don't.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But see, if you choose to defend and kill, then you can expect the other party will do the same.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the war will never end.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, violence will always bring more violence.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, somebody has to take it first and not do it back.
[SPEAKER_04]: And even then, it's not necessarily that other people will stop.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you don't care about other people's actions.
[SPEAKER_04]: You care about your mental state and whether you have found the peace internally.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why dhamma, really, it's not compatible.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you want to, you know, govern the world and engage with the world.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even the Buddha himself had to make a choice, whether he'll be the supreme righteous ruler of the world or go and become the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_04]: He couldn't do both.
[SPEAKER_04]: He was either or.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, this is the same.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have a choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which one do you value more?
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, take it... take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, you can't expect results from both.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, oh, I'm on the peaceful mind, although I am breaking the precepts, in quite a serious way, if it comes to killing and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, but, does it mean that, let's say, for the people who, well, have so much attachment to, let's say, you know, to their country or maybe to their families, whatever may happen, do you think that, well, that they are going to be more peaceful if they, let's say,
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, the wild elephant, unless... until it's trained, it will be more peaceful in the wilderness of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's not going to result in peace and happiness we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just perpetuation of the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, by perpetuating your attachments, you're perpetuating your basis for suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't suffer because the war started.
[SPEAKER_04]: You suffer because things that are dear to you are under a threat.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you have nothing dear to you, you cannot suffer even if you yourself is being attacked.
[SPEAKER_04]: Plain and simple.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you choose to protect your attachments, that is fine, that is your choice, but that means, okay, you are choosing, basically, perpetuation of dependence on things that keep you not calm, and not peaceful, and at threat, and not at ease.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's exactly what I would have meant by...
[SPEAKER_04]: Acquisitions, that was the word.
[SPEAKER_04]: The things that belong to you, that they expose you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because of them, you suffer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because of them, you're liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: So... And same with the idea of nationality as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the country, that's like one of the subtlest thoughts, the thoughts that the monk would abandon.
[SPEAKER_04]: First, the coarse sensuality, the coarse cruelty, but then thoughts of belonging to my clan, clanhood, family, country, all of those ideas of identity.
[SPEAKER_04]: Those are also your possessions.
[SPEAKER_04]: And because of that, you will suffer.
[SPEAKER_07]: Would Buddha defend his life while being physically... No.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, he said if you have even an evil thought towards your attackers while they're butchering you, you haven't fulfilled his instruction.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, let alone if you actually fight back.
[SPEAKER_08]: And how would you address the evil thoughts?
[SPEAKER_04]: First, by not acting out of them, because the evil thoughts become a problem when you start doing things on account of them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Having them arise in your mind, it's not a problem in itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you do something out of body because of evil thoughts, if you start saying things because of evil thoughts, that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, don't do anything by body, by speech, and then evil thoughts will not have as much power over you as they did when you used to act out of them.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, that wild elephant that's chained in the beginning, every thought will be thought of that, you know, great unrestrained wilderness.
[SPEAKER_04]: But once he comes down, gets used to the environment, those thoughts will not be as pressuring as before.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's their training, being able to take them without acting out of them.
[SPEAKER_08]: Do you believe that we live through our mind?
[SPEAKER_08]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, to me, it seems like we are, like, rationalizing everything.
[SPEAKER_08]: And, eh... that we are not, like, living from the... from the heart, that we are... Well, again, that in itself is a rationalization, that you must live from the heart.
[SPEAKER_04]: Who... who says... who said that?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like... we didn't all agree on that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not all people agree with that we all must live from the heart.
[SPEAKER_04]: And what does that mean for you?
[SPEAKER_04]: What does that mean for me?
[SPEAKER_04]: What does that mean... can mean different things.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then you realize, yeah, rationalization, some people do it more, some people do it less, but even then, you have to be doing something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if you think, I'll just stop thinking and live the life fully, that's another rationalization that you're choosing to act upon.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you want to really recognize, like, where your action is taking you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Are they adding fuel to the wild mind or are they calming it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Are they helping you keep an eye on that mind when it changes or not?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or are they making you forget about it?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, one comment with regards to this is, and I would be happy if you could then maybe expand on this or maybe add a few reflections.
[SPEAKER_06]: My experience so far was drawing both on my own personal experience and also on the experiences I've had with other friends and colleagues who
[SPEAKER_06]: There's just this utter rootlessness in the sense of
[SPEAKER_06]: There's no room for sīla whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_06]: And this was, you know, my experience as well.
[SPEAKER_06]: And listening to this, I was again reminded of this, you know, finding myself in certain places with certain experiences I couldn't really handle.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I didn't know what to do with them.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I had absolutely no anchoring whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_06]: And what I found helpful sometimes was just, you know, engaging in something very physical or something very simple, just so that I was, you know, anchored.
[SPEAKER_06]: And after that, I could pursue, so continue with, let's say, contemplative practice and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not putting it aside completely, that is to say, but it was through these experiences that I realized how important this
[SPEAKER_06]: Anchorages.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, this was my entry into the realm of sīla.
[SPEAKER_06]: How naive I was, in a certain sense, thinking that, well, you know, this is... yeah, okay, we start with sīla.
[SPEAKER_06]: Give me the meat.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, give me the meat, you know.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm not really interested in the soup and the veggies.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just, you know, I want the raw meat stuff.
[SPEAKER_06]: I was just wondering, in what way would it be perhaps possible to articulate the importance of sīla so that
[SPEAKER_06]: You know, someone in contemporary setting would realize this without necessarily having to go several years and then... Well, in the way I'm doing it.
[SPEAKER_04]: 300 talks on YouTube, I don't know how many audio hours, just repeating the same.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's... most of it is exactly for that reason.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because people are... people hear the Buddhist teaching, they're interested in it, but then they want to skip the training part.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, to make things worse, you have modern techniques and centers and meditations and monasteries that encourage you to kind of, okay, yeah, keep it, but this is really the meat of the practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it becomes even more distant and people don't even recognize, you know, people might take on the sīla, but not recognize how the training comes through it.
[SPEAKER_04]: They take the precepts because they're buddhists and so on, but they don't train in them.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there's a big difference.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why it's sīlavāda paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's within the first three fetters that they're abandoned.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's not a small thing, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: One way or the other, eh...
[SPEAKER_04]: People's minds, generally, regardless of the culture and education, everything else, are used to, you know, acting out of sensuality, acting out of your own desires, which naturally then brings that whole expectation, okay, I want to practice, give me the result, and then, you know, you don't want to be patient about it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, you just keep repeating it and those who are willing to hear it will do so.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, but my experience so far was that usually... And also don't give any compromise.
[SPEAKER_04]: There is no, oh, this is helpful.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_04]: The Buddha was quite clear.
[SPEAKER_04]: If there is no right view, there is no meditation.
[SPEAKER_04]: If somebody wants to practice meditation without the right view, without a virtue,
[SPEAKER_04]: Without training in precepts, that's not possible, at least not in the Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, now they can at least know that, okay, in this teaching, this is what's taught.
[SPEAKER_04]: I cannot mistake it for something else or misrepresent it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, they can choose to follow a different teacher or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's no problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the problem is when people misrepresent what the Buddha was teaching and then think that this is the practice of dharma which has nothing to do with it or quite opposite, directly opposite to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why the Buddha would refer to those things like pernicious views.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not because, you know, people are evil in them, but because, see, now they think they're practicing dharma by doing meditation technique, having precepts secondary over the weekend or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: And now they will not make the effort to practice the dhamma or find out what a dhamma is, because they think that's what the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: Full stop.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the worst.
[SPEAKER_04]: At least, you know, if you prefer it and you do it, but at least if you know that that's not what the Buddha was teaching, well, there is still a possibility for you, at some point in the future, to come back to it and maybe do it rightly.
[SPEAKER_04]: But not if you have misrepresented it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but I mean, but it seems to me that, well, in the perception of people, it seems to be, like, logical.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, this is, as I said, it is good to keep some moral standards in the normal times, but if you are threatened, so to say, they would say, yeah, I mean... Yeah, so then you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Put your attachments first or your moral standards first.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you can't have it both.
[SPEAKER_08]: Why wouldn't you kill to protect your family?
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: Up to you.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not saying you shouldn't or you shouldn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm saying what the moral standards are.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can't have moral standards intact and break them.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's simply a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you choose to kill, means you chose to put your attachment first and your moral standards second.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you choose to not kill, means you stayed with your moral standards.
[SPEAKER_04]: Choice is yours.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: Either a dead... either a dead moral or a dead wife.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_08]: Either a dead moral or a dead wife.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_07]: Let's understand this.
[SPEAKER_07]: If you have... Bradley Pipeline Life.
[SPEAKER_07]: This is hypothetically, but you can save one billion lives or kill one who wants to kill them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, the standard Hitler question, yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: So, what is the moral question here?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, the moral question is that you're responsible for your choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the moral question is that your choice is not on the level of world and other people, it's on the level of you choosing to do so.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you choose to kill one person, you did commit murder.
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't matter if you save thousands.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, which is more important to you?
[SPEAKER_04]: To measure by the standards of the world or to keep your moral standards?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or at least the buddhist moral standards?
[SPEAKER_07]: Do you think he would not say what
[SPEAKER_04]: No?
[SPEAKER_04]: If it means killing, yeah, absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_04]: He's incapable of killing.
[SPEAKER_07]: Absolutely impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: And now, you create yourself a problem of another philosophical question.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not that I want to get into it, but what's... Who determines the value of life?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is it the sheer quantity of life?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is better... a thousand is better than one?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or is there a quality to life?
[SPEAKER_04]: One wise person is better than a hundred immoral killers?
[SPEAKER_04]: Who decides that?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you're going to end up in a big sort of entanglement.
[SPEAKER_04]: In reality, that's going to result in exactly people doing what they want and justifying it with some moral standards they did themselves a breaking.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because they ignore the basic rule is that doesn't matter what the world says, doesn't matter what the state of the world is, you are responsible for your choices and your actions.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you start putting that first, then killing will be felt differently.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if it's...
[SPEAKER_07]: I'll go to hardcore.
[SPEAKER_07]: There is a type of a psychopath who wants to destroy all Earth, and Buddha has power to kill him.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah?
[SPEAKER_06]: So, the whole cosmos.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay, what would he do?
[SPEAKER_07]: Not kill him.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's an easy question.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's easy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not kill him, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: This story, there was like one murderous guy...
[SPEAKER_08]: Observe the one billionaire.
[SPEAKER_02]: There was one murderous guy, Angulimala, who was killing thousands of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And Buddha could have a chance, but he didn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was teaching him dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So he got...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not his problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: If a thousand people die, it's not because the Buddha didn't kill that guy.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's because that guy chose to kill a thousand people.
[SPEAKER_07]: But, eh, I think that he has some knowledge about this universe also, and, eh, perhaps he believed or knew that, eh, there is, eh, the old stuff will be rebuilt again.
[SPEAKER_04]: Maybe, but say, following your argument, eh, he had knowledge about the universe, greater than ours, and he said you should never kill.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there you go.
[SPEAKER_04]: He probably had even greater reasons than we can fathom to say, no, never, you should never kill.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I agree with that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Does this apply... where is the border, the meaning of life?
[SPEAKER_05]: Does this apply only to people or to animals and plants and so on?
[SPEAKER_05]: Where is the border?
[SPEAKER_04]: It applies to any creatures that are capable of choices and action, which is why animals are so screwed.
[SPEAKER_04]: They can't stop it.
[SPEAKER_04]: They don't have enough power to reflect and make right choices, which is why it's so hard to leave the animal realm, as the Buddha was saying.
[SPEAKER_07]: Did Buddha have some powers to calm people down with his essence, just to be in front of them, so they won't do something they want to do just through their emotions?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I mean, yes and no, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_04]: He couldn't take control or responsibility for their actions, but
[SPEAKER_04]: Sometimes if people were calmed down by his demeanor, it's because they already kind of recognized the value of such demeanor.
[SPEAKER_04]: But some people didn't even recognize that he would have been the Buddha or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yes, some people were calmed by him, but because they already kind of valued that type of appearance or behavior and maybe reminded them of that.
[SPEAKER_06]: that's basically, in a certain sense, a minor elephant in the room, namely the situation in Ukraine.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, I was just curious if you could maybe share a few words on how maybe you, as a monastic, relate to events of this sort and what would you suggest or advise to someone who is still part of the world, so, in a certain sense,
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you know, something like that happens, and then it's all over the news, and you don't want to be completely flooded by it, but in a certain sense, you still, because you're part of the world, you still maybe want to contribute in one way or another, or I don't know, by, I don't know, helping people who come over.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can, for instance, do this in in the academic setting, because there will be specific things that we can do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so you help those that need help, keep the precepts,
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: They're quite clear what you should do and what you shouldn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, yeah, probably don't become addicted to reading news as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's quite a thing in itself.
[SPEAKER_07]: So, yeah, again, a very simple answer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Would you advise...
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't really matter if it's a war in Ukraine or anywhere else.
[SPEAKER_04]: The principles remain intact, unchanged.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you want to practice, or at least maintain the framework of some sort of Buddhist practice, you have to put those standards first.
[SPEAKER_07]: How do you define pleasure?
[SPEAKER_07]: Can someone get meditation for pleasure?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: And be addicted to meditation?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's what we call wrong meditation.
[SPEAKER_04]: And be addicted to mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't think you can be addicted to mindfulness, because it's not something you're doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, yes, certainly people can get addicted to their wrong meditation if they're doing it for the sake of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: They don't want to be bothered, they don't want to deal with things, and they justify it with my meditation practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's quite common.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, regarding meditation, so you sometimes say that there is no jhāna without right view and things like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe I'm quoting you not quite correctly, but I mean, but we know from the sutra that there were ascetics who practiced jhāna without being
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, I say there is no right meditation without a right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't say there is no jhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: However, having jhāna without having right view today, it's almost impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you have jhāna, it means you pretty much have cleared your mind and developed it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the reason why the Buddha praised the jhāna as the right form of meditation is because it's along the lines of development of the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you... and that's exactly what some people, after being ascetics and followers of different practices, had, even his previous teachers, neither perception nor perception or higher states of development, he said they had very little dust in their eyes on account of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: He would have needed to teach them one sentence or two.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, in other words, the jhāna meditation is not what people think meditation is.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a development of mind that's basically freeing you from ignorance, even if you don't necessarily know it.
[SPEAKER_04]: To the extent that the Buddha knew it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why some people who have committed, like Bahia, who practiced as a naked, as a wood-bark ascetic,
[SPEAKER_04]: For who knows how long, he thought he was genuinely an Arahant, because there was nothing else disturbing him at all, in any shape or form.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, he found out that there is an actual Arahant.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he went to meet the Buddha, and all the Buddha said is, in the scene, let there just be the scene, in the heard, in the sensed, touched, taught, and he became an Arahant right there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Wow, he was so lucky.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, he did the work probably for decades of his ascetic practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means, yes, he didn't have the right view, but he was doing the right practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Today, that somebody can do the right practice without the right view and develop jhānas with all the knowledge of the suttas, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: They would have to find out that that's what they're doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what you have today is people doing the opposite stuff that's not found in the suttas, claiming it's the jhānas from the suttas, and then they arrive at the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the right view, I mean, eh... right view is not equivalent to sense-restraint, I mean, per se.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: It comes out of sense-restraint and understanding the science of your mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But for jhānas, let's say, sense-restraint and things like that are sufficient.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: For jhānas, sensory strength is a prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_04]: Understanding the entire domain of sensuality, the danger, gratification and withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, you can dwell in the pleasure of safety, on account of freedom from the trap and the bait that māra sets up.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, you'll be in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: And see, all of these things are on the level of understanding and contemplation that the Buddha talked about.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not on the level of meditation technique that people like to think jhānas are.
[SPEAKER_04]: But again, like in I don't know how many suttas, there is no Noble Eightfold Path without the Right View, let alone Right Samādhi without the Right View.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not possible.
[SPEAKER_04]: Simply not possible.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what did those ascetics didn't... what did they not understand?
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, who could practice jhānas, say, back then?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, they obviously understood.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, they got the jhānas because they abandoned centrality completely.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_04]: An outsider can uproot the upādāna of sensuality, the upādāna of the views, sīlabhāta-paramāsa, but they can't uproot the attavāda.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's the only thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: That self-view, for that you do need Buddha's instruction.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, but imagine now, teaching freedom from attavāda to puthujjana, who is not free from sensuality or anything else,
[SPEAKER_04]: And now imagine teaching freedom from Atavāda to a pūtujana who is free from sensuality and from everything else.
[SPEAKER_04]: Accept that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Who's gonna... what do you think?
[SPEAKER_04]: Who's gonna be easier to teach?
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly the difference.
[SPEAKER_04]: One of them did the work.
[SPEAKER_04]: A lot of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the problem with today's meditation is, see, even jhāna then is quite a lot of work.
[SPEAKER_04]: Quite a lot of clearing the mess from your mind, withdrawal from sensuality, seeing the danger of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But today's notion of meditation is
[SPEAKER_04]: How can I avoid all of that work, or turn my work into something mindlessly mechanical, that I'll adhere to, be told to, don't have to think about too much, or doubt, or experience uncertainty, and then I have the experience, and that's the jhāna, and that's the sensations, and that's the vedanās, or whatever else, and that's my liberation.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that, in itself, is a completely wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: What types of meditation do you suggest are good to practice?
[SPEAKER_04]: Keeping the precepts, guarding of the sense doors, being mindful, moderate in your eating, and keeping an eye on your intentions.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's samādhi.
[SPEAKER_04]: Everything else you do, instead of that, is going to be done out of the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you get the right view, if you see the way out of suffering internally,
[SPEAKER_04]: Understand the escape, understand the no volatile path, then keep the right view and that will be your samādhi.
[SPEAKER_04]: Protect it, that will be your samādhi.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, right view means right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_04]: No right view means no right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't do right meditation without knowing, basically, the way out of suffering, which is what the right view is.
[SPEAKER_04]: You do the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practicing the right way of living.
[SPEAKER_04]: The gradual training.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's that's all.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there is no mention of such thing as a meditation technique in a gradual training, ever.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the suttas, gradual training, when you fulfill that, when you're ready for seclusion, withdrawal, then you go that next step, then you develop jhāna, then you dwell in that, and all of the asavas are exhausted, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Everything else that that's today regarded as meditation and meditation techniques came probably, I don't know, four or five, six centuries later, by people that were studying Buddhism, not practicing it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're welcome to do whatever you want to do, but the most important thing is don't misrepresent or don't think that that's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: And many people would think
[SPEAKER_04]: Actually, if you read the suttas, you find out that he never mentioned anything like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And when he did, it was mentioned in a very clear context.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, now you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Either you carry on with a contemporary idea of what the Buddha was teaching, or find out what the Buddha was teaching, and then choose which one you want to practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the worst is when people conflate the two.
[SPEAKER_06]: I have a question with regards to this.
[SPEAKER_06]: Would you say that, for instance, these, let's say, techniques and...
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, we don't necessarily have to go into some of the more contemporary ones, but in general, would you say that they are completely erroneous or that they were merely an attempt to formalize
[SPEAKER_06]: See, the problem is, can you systematize and formalize your motivation behind your actions, your states of mind, your intentions?
[SPEAKER_04]: Can you put that into system?
[SPEAKER_06]: I agree with that.
[SPEAKER_06]: But the thing is that if somebody knows what he or she is doing, might be using this form of technique, and it could be helpful because they know... For what?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, for instance, just for, say, having a more structured way of dealing it.
[SPEAKER_06]: And if you know that you need to be mindful of or take into account, say, your motivation and whatnot, this might be helpful.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you don't, of course, mean that, well, I just follow these ten
[SPEAKER_06]: You have certain steps that allow you to just, you know, have a better way of dealing with background motivations.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm going to trivialize now, but if you have some sort of a seated meditation that is focused on something, this can be a useful setting for you to be more aware of, you know,
[SPEAKER_06]: Now, what often happens, that was my experience, is that people just say, you know, you just sit and then you follow breath and if something comes, you know, you go back to the breath and whatnot and you completely lose any sense of that what arises
[SPEAKER_06]: So, you know, you can either go... you can use a technique in a way that becomes very mechanical, or you can use it as a tool.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let me draw an analogy.
[SPEAKER_06]: For instance, you can use, say, a certain weightlifting move.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just to perfect this particular weightlifting move, and you become a master snatch or clean.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or you can use it to improve your explosiveness, because you want to achieve a certain something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, no, I understand what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what I'm trying to get to the bottom of is, what is the technique helpful for?
[SPEAKER_04]: What is that carry-over?
[SPEAKER_04]: Snatch carries over into explosive power.
[SPEAKER_04]: What is your meditation technique focusing carry-over into?
[SPEAKER_04]: What is it helpful for?
[SPEAKER_06]: That's... that's why I wanna... My response would be, for instance, that it could be useful for sensory strength, in the sense of that it allows you a more structured manner of basically even coming to terms or seeing the the way that
[SPEAKER_06]: You are usually not sense-restrained, because senses have these tendencies to go one way or another.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, see, now that's the problem, because that perpetuity is the wrong view, where the sense-restraint is.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't accidentally break your sense-restraint.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's always a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's always a matter of giving in.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, but if you think that it's a question of catching the right moment of your thoughts, that your meditation technique helps you, you are perpetuating a view that the sensory strain or that the problem of sensuality comes from the world.
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_04]: It comes from your choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you cannot systematize your state of mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you do, it's because you're avoiding responsibility for the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: And people have a strong tendency to systematize, because if you stay on the level of state of mind, you stay on the level of hindrances, you stay on the level of uncertainty, doubt, discomfort, pressure.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly where that comes out of a sensory strain.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you do the precepts rightly, you are forcing your mind to grow towards abandoning hindrances and developing jhāna, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you do a technique,
[SPEAKER_04]: means you're managing the symptoms that you don't want to bear.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't want to endure the uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't want to endure the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: You want to systematize it, so you know what to do, so you don't endure the pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you basically shoot yourself in the foot.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, precepts created a base for practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Meditation technique took it away.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why I keep saying, if you sit down to meditate because you're disturbed, you need to calm down, fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, you just need to calm down.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, drawing these parallels of how it's helpful to this or that, it just perpetuates around the wrong view of where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's not in the world, it's not in the sense objects, it's not in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's in your choices in regard to it, that are rooted in greed, aversion, delusion, as simple as that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And no systematical way can that always contain it rightly for everyone, universally.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because every mind has to see it for themselves.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: I especially understand that the point about uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let me just give one last attempt, maybe, in this direction.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, the question or my point would be the following, so that...
[SPEAKER_06]: Even, of course, it is your own response to a certain something that is crucial.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sometimes it's difficult to basically be able to... No, not necessarily a response of any kind.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well...
[SPEAKER_04]: Intentional action.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, intentional positioning or taking on a certain attitude towards something.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sometimes what's problematic is that you don't really
[SPEAKER_06]: Things can happen either very quickly or very messy, in a very messy manner.
[SPEAKER_06]: How technique might be helpful is by simply, you know, putting yourself in a specific position that might be uncomfortable in many different ways, because people, you know, there are just so many different things that crop up during meditation that could be... that allow for plenty of... that allow a lot of opportunities for you
[SPEAKER_06]: Such as?
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, for instance, you know, if you find yourself
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, if you find yourself in a very specific situation, say, in the middle of a city, you know, you see an attractive woman...
[SPEAKER_06]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_06]: And a lot of things happen so quickly, that it is only, when it's only over, you know, you realize it.
[SPEAKER_06]: If, however, if you're in a specific situation, you might get a certain, say, thought about a certain person you find attractive, you can notice how you start responding to it, and you recognize the whole event and also can shift your attitude or position towards it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Again, the problem is not in how quickly things move.
[SPEAKER_04]: The problem is in you simply not knowing where the gateway of your intention is.
[SPEAKER_04]: And no amount of studying or slowing down the speed will help you that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Again, this will perpetuate the wrong problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thinking that meditation helps you with what you assume the problem is.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's not what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_04]: The problem is not how much you're over... First of all, if you're in that environment, how do you deal with it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you sit cross-legged in the middle of the road?
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: You keep the precepts and you endure the discomfort and you don't let your eye go where they shouldn't go.
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't make choices on account of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you already know that.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's on the level of knowledge and cultivation from beforehand.
[SPEAKER_04]: But this idea of slowing down to catch my response in the moment, again, assumes that the problem is in this involuntary sight, sound, smell, taste, touches and response.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_04]: The problem is in intentional avoidance of discomfort, intentional prolonging of pleasure, intentional distraction and ignoring of a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: And again, the more you commit to watching moments, the further away from recognizing the states of mind you are, of this kind.
[SPEAKER_06]: Again, it's...
[SPEAKER_06]: I just think that, you know, there... it's... it's...
[SPEAKER_06]: Sometimes it's difficult or...
[SPEAKER_06]: Let's put it differently.
[SPEAKER_06]: It takes a while for one to realize or recognize, just recognize, you know, the differences between, say, a response and reaction.
[SPEAKER_06]: Like you said, you know, people sometimes say, well, you know, things just happened and, you know, then every... just a lot of events unfolded.
[SPEAKER_06]: But then, if you start to discern or discriminate what is going on and you acquire this ability to see that, then you see that it didn't just evolve or happen, but there were a lot of steps where you basically
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: The steps you're taking are not on the level you're observing.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, apples and oranges, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: The steps you are taking are the steps on the level of choice, that you know, in the broadest sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: Acceptance, as Buddha said, he welcomes, he delights, he entertains the notions of centrality.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, say you saw something that attracted your attention in the street, you looked once, now you feel bad, you realize.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there is a choice there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I look again?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I give in to the weakness or do I endure the pain?
[SPEAKER_04]: And there's no meditation technique, there's no place for meditation.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is a meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: I understand, I understand.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, endure the discomfort of not letting it.
[SPEAKER_04]: The Buddha said he doesn't let the eyes look at the unsuitable things.
[SPEAKER_04]: He doesn't let air go to the domain of unsuitable sounds.
[SPEAKER_04]: They would provoke lust, infatuation and those states of mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's not on the level of mechanical watching of the moments, analyzing, slowing down the speed.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's on the level of choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's not something you can have in front of you as an object of your senses that you can observe or focus on.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, I mean,
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in my experience, in meditation, let's say, some meditation techniques, maybe, I mean, it seems, so when Sebastian explains what he does, it seems to me that I'm doing something similar.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it seems like it helps you to do, let's say, right choices, I'd say, or not to do bad choices, simply because you are more aware of the things that's going on, so to say.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, and it can't be helpful in this way, I mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe you would notice it also, without this technique, but it still helps you to come back faster, so to say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Come back to what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, to the choice that you have just done, or, say, you looked in the direction where you shouldn't have looked.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_03]: And and and well, I mean, normally you would continue in this direction and only afterwards you see, okay, I shouldn't have done this.
[SPEAKER_03]: But in in in when when I say when the mind is calmed, through meditation, you can recognize this, well, just at the moment when you when you just looked at it, just came, made one glance in the... No, but see, now you're talking about the environment when you're not calm, in the environment when you're calm.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, which one is it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you sit in the middle of the road to calm your mind?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, but... Or you're talking about a different instance?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I mean, I'd say that meditation has an impact also on your being amidst the road, I'd say.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's a... it's like a... it's like this general...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, you also were saying about... speaking about
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'm not denying the calmness of mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm denying that the focus in practice results in contributing to, you know, your intentions.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because what are you focusing on?
[SPEAKER_04]: Can you focus on the intention of your mind?
[SPEAKER_04]: What is the object of your focusing in your meditation?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's my question, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah, I mean, it's... How should I say?
[SPEAKER_03]: For me, it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, I shouldn't call it focusing, really, but it's more like you try to stay somehow with your breath, and it's like putting some...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, and observe your intentions.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, I'd say...
[SPEAKER_04]: Sorry, sorry, sorry.
[SPEAKER_04]: Absorb the intentions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Observe, sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: Observe.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, observe your intentions, or, like, your thoughts, what you are thinking about, and try not to, let's say, not to get caught in them, in a manner that you sort of
[SPEAKER_04]: How do you... how do you get caught in thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, when you start dealing too much with the content, let's say, if you...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, if you...
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say, you have some some worldly problem, whatever, and you start solving it, instead of, let's say, trying to understand why am I thinking about it, what is, I mean, more general perspective, and what are my intentions, basically, in all this stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I'd say, like...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how does that meditation technique...
[SPEAKER_04]: It helps you understand the intentions and not be caught up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I'd say it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm... it seems to me that it's... or I may use a simile.
[SPEAKER_03]: It seems to me it's like having, like, say, a white table and putting something that you want to sort out on this white table.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so that you can see clearly where the where the things are.
[SPEAKER_03]: And another situation is like when you when your mind is confused, it's like having like... Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Great.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly what not what problem is not.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, having things cluttered or sorted out, you already have intention behind.
[SPEAKER_04]: You already have an intention to sort things out because they bother you.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're already bothered by things that are not sorted out on the level of intentions.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't sort your intentions like you would sort things on the table.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, when you want to sort out your thoughts, you do that because you want to avoid suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't want to endure it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't want to be unmoved by it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, when you just revolve, spinning out of control, you do that because you don't want to avoid suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Either way, you are managing the pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: Either way, meditation techniques is taking you in the directions away from where your intentions are, because both are rooted in intention of avoiding pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: And no amount of looking and sorting things out and catching the details will change the intention that all of that is rooted in.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, as I said, already, and also, it perpetuates the wrong view that the mind gets disturbed by things and speed of things, and that's not true.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is a completely wrong view.
[SPEAKER_04]: What the Buddha described, the root of every disturbance in the mind is greed,
[SPEAKER_04]: Aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Things that you do by choice and intention.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, too many women passing you, does not disturb your mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: Too many sounds disturbing your ear, does not disturb your mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: Choosing greed, choosing aversion, choosing delusion, disturbs your mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, now you have a meditation technique that helps you calm the disturbed mind and at the same time perpetuates the view that the disturbance came of the world and things moving too fast.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, your meditation techniques keeps your wrong view revolving.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it doesn't recognize the weight.
[SPEAKER_04]: Disturbance didn't come from things being too quick, or too slow, or too many, or one, or too few.
[SPEAKER_04]: It came because I still choose aversion, delusion, and greed when they present themselves.
[SPEAKER_04]: I haven't endured things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: I haven't upgraded the sīla on the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't see the danger in the slightest fault on the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not moderate enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't live in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whatever parts of the gradual training that the Buddha listed as a prerequisite, you must be lacking somewhere, because if you don't, the mind would not be disturbed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because there are no more choices and intentions rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thus, if the mind is not disturbed, what use is to calm it by sorting the tools on the table?
[SPEAKER_04]: If you need to sort them out, great, but has nothing to do with the development of where the problem is, the gateway.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, I'd say, like, being in seclusion, I mean, it's also...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a question to what extent you can be in seclusion, I'd say, even in the monastic environment, yeah?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I mean, it may be, I could say, that it's not because I'm lacking in seclusion as much as probably is needed.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I don't think seclusion...
[SPEAKER_04]: I just listed those examples.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't think that's a problem for most people.
[SPEAKER_04]: That comes later.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even the seclusion in the gradual training comes far later.
[SPEAKER_04]: First, basically, the person develops the right view, becomes a sotāpanna, and then he's ready for seclusion, seclusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: For most people, seclusion is just, oh, just, again, some sort of controlled environment that will not disturb me as much, because I don't know how to deal with the disturbances that come, because I don't see where the gateway is.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's fine, but you need to recognize, again, the only way to start practicing rightly is to recognize where that gateway is.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's not in speed of things, it's not in the environment, environment around you, it's not in the sense objects, it's not in anything observable, it's not in your body.
[SPEAKER_04]: Gateway is welcoming, delighting, entertaining, greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why, literally, when someone says, give me one, one, just short instructions, they ask the Buddha, and he would say, whatever you know that is unwholesome, rooted, greed, aversion, delusion, don't do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Three months later, arahants.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that is...
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so I use that as a standard.
[SPEAKER_04]: Greed, aversion, delusion on the level of thoughts, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: I will endure it, not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: I will not do anything on account of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's how it will fade.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it needs to be brought up to that absolute core level.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if it's not on that level, it's because the gradual training has not been taken up sufficiently.
[SPEAKER_04]: Restrained by the rules, seeing danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not like all this is allowable.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's no such thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: If it's rooted in greed, aversion, delusion, it's not allowable, even if it's not against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the principle that most people don't take on as a practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: They take on sīla, but they don't take the practice on account of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can be calm in your mind with various techniques, but you've got to be aware that at the same time you are perpetuating the wrong view of where the problem really is, and it's not there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the disturbances do not come on account of you not having watched your thoughts enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, you know, the world overwhelming you or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it comes on account of intentional choice of greed, aversion, delusion, every single time.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you stop doing those, the mind will have to come down, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to watch your thoughts all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, you have to watch your choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: Choices.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Would you say that, for instance...
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, let's leave aside the term technique, okay?
[SPEAKER_06]: It's too... too... too... laden with connotations.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, maybe ways or creating conditions, circumstances, where you...
[SPEAKER_06]: This for me...
[SPEAKER_06]: The reason why I'm asking all this, because this for me was important in the sense of
[SPEAKER_06]: For instance, or delusion, you know, it's it's one thing to say it, but then another thing how it manifests.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, so, hold on, what makes you think you recognized it?
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, I mean, you know it when it manifests itself, but you
[SPEAKER_06]: However, it's sometimes difficult to see how it manifests in specific contexts.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, what it means for you?
[SPEAKER_06]: So, how how it affects you in very concrete contexts?
[SPEAKER_06]: So... Give me an example.
[SPEAKER_06]: An example?
[SPEAKER_04]: Of seeing delusion and seeing the specific context of delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: What do you mean by it?
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, maybe, you know,
[SPEAKER_06]: It would be just, for instance, during the seated meditation, or what have you, and having something appear in your mind, and then just seeing how entangled you become, and how
[SPEAKER_06]: The emotive responses are towards that, where you want to simply cling to that, or you don't want to get away from that particular thing.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then, the thing itself, you realize, it's not really that important, but the overall response that was evoked is.
[SPEAKER_04]: But why is that a problem?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, because you feel that... Ah, because it's painful.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you want to get rid of discomfort.
[SPEAKER_06]: Uh...
[SPEAKER_06]: I see where you're going.
[SPEAKER_04]: It comes back to that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Acting out of feeling, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's my point, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but I mean...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you recognize that the pain is the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you analyzing your responses, I will root to you just because you don't want this pain to be here.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you are acting out of aversion towards pain.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, but see, that way you can recognize aversion again.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, well, you haven't.
[SPEAKER_04]: See, you're recognizing what you placed in front to be, but see, you think you're now understanding greed and stuff, while in reality, you're currently in the state of aversion, that you're fully gripped and you're not seeing, because you're looking at something you think is greed.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's it's obviously... and again, mind you, none of these...
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not I'm not saying you shouldn't sit down quietly in a non-disturbed environment and think about things.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because whenever you started to describe to me your meditation, you don't... you describe, basically, you sit down and you start thinking about things.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, that was just, you know, I... there are ways of maybe just... And that's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't want to be in the middle of the city and I must be able to meditate here.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, you probably won't be able to.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or even contemplate things.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you want to
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, yeah, you need to recognize where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the problem is always in present action rooted in presently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: And even if that's unclear, or sometimes it's more clear, sometimes not that clear,
[SPEAKER_04]: That comes and goes.
[SPEAKER_04]: What doesn't come and go is precepts, virtue, danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you still do see your intentions and state of mind on that level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, maybe you don't see it on the subtlest level of the thought, but it's only because, obviously, you're still on some level welcoming it elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not because you haven't, you know, caught a right moment to spot it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's not that a train has passed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, I missed it now.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: State of mind endures.
[SPEAKER_04]: You are the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you're unclear about it, it's not because it evaded you, it's because you haven't sufficiently stopped acting out of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: You stopped... you haven't sufficiently stopped entertaining it and welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hence, the disturbances are still present in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you give an example of how to preserve the choices?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you get up in the morning and basically see what you want to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then see why you want to do those things in the most generic way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, oh, I want to go and see such and such.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is that rooted?
[SPEAKER_04]: Am I bored at home?
[SPEAKER_04]: Am I lonely?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I need company?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I just want a distraction?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, you know, I'm going there to learn or something?
[SPEAKER_04]: And already all these choices are there.
[SPEAKER_04]: You just need to start asking those questions to yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's the practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the contemplation.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, you see where intention... Well, then, spend every day of your life not acting out of anything that's rooted in sensual desire, in aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the purification of the mind will have to happen, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is much harder to do, and keep an eye on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So see, oh, now, okay, so now I have to change my lifestyle as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: I can't go left and right and pay no attention to things around me, if I have to, you know, restrain my own intentions.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not going to be possible.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's the whole lifestyle choices then start to change and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's much more fundamental and much more harder than if, like that, you know, your duties, sit for half an hour, calm down, feel the sensations, watch your nostrils and then go about your life.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, they would never said that, anything remotely like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was always, yeah, you want to improve your life, stop acting out of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: To the extent you stop acting out of those states of mind, to that extent, your mind will be more peaceful, more pliable, it will listen to you, it will be more trained.
[SPEAKER_04]: You do it more, great, it will be even more so.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the practice of, pretty much, they will take you from somebody who doesn't have the right view to somebody who has the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, from somebody who had the right view, could take you to abandon sensuality and everything else.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because these, as I said, these disturbances that nobody wants, even people that don't practice, want to practice, nobody wants to disturb mind, they don't come on account of the world, they don't come on account of anything through your senses, they come on account of your choices.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the only place they can come through.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's what the Buddha meant by that, even if the highway robbers are chopping your limbs, if you hate them, you haven't fulfilled my teaching, because that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Your limbs being chopped was not a problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was you acting out of aversion.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you're able to hate them, means, oh, you have not uprooted it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what if you enjoy nature, for example?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also sensual pleasure to some extent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, it depends.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not necessarily always going to be rooted in the same motivation.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's not like I'll never go into nature, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just you have to... Each time you want to go into nature, you have to know why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Are you doing it just, you know, yeah, you want some nature, peaceful freedom from people?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or are you doing it because, you know, you're a bit bored, lonely in your apartment?
[SPEAKER_04]: So it's like, oh, so now you're doing it because you want to avoid the discomfort?
[SPEAKER_04]: And another occasion you might do it because you need exercise or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: So it's not, it's not set in stone every single time.
[SPEAKER_07]: But how does someone know what is desire when he speaks about going into woods or meditating or being a void of suffering?
[SPEAKER_07]: This can be desires also.
[SPEAKER_07]: But it's beneficial.
[SPEAKER_07]: What what can be desire also?
[SPEAKER_07]: Desire for not being... for not suffering.
[SPEAKER_07]: Desire for going into woods and having...
[SPEAKER_04]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's... that's what it meant.
[SPEAKER_04]: Desire is to be abandoned by the means of desire.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, because of that desire, you will now start keeping the precepts, not acting out of desire, and you will lose all the desires.
[SPEAKER_07]: Will you lose them?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, because you stop...
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, again, now you're guessing, because you're not at the end stage of not having any desire.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, unless you commit to the path and free yourself from desire, you won't know for yourself whether you're going to lose them or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, whichever answer I give you, is going to be a speculative one.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_07]: I have a question about breath.
[SPEAKER_07]: Did Buddha just talk about
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, first, he spoke about ānāpānasati, the mindfulness or non-forgetfulness of breathing, to people that already had the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, they already knew what, you know, freedom from desire is, freedom from suffering, and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, the way he spoke about it, it's... no, it's nothing to do with, like, prana or energies.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was more of just mindfulness of your choice to breathe.
[SPEAKER_04]: I should breathe in like this, I should breathe out like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: I should breathe in with a state of mind like this, I should breathe in with a state of mind like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it was quite different from the other kind of breeding practices of India at the time.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know if it's the same time or around the same time.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, yeah, it had absolutely no connotations of any energies or things like that to be developed.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was just pure non-forgetfulness, just so you're mindful.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why it's called mindfulness of breeding.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have a question in this similar line.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it seems to me that, well, it was the saying that I was, that I wanted to refer to, actually, that the desire has to be abandoned by means of desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe, I mean, aversion and also by the means of aversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, I mean, like,
[SPEAKER_03]: Isn't it... for instance, if somebody meditates in order to get rid of, let's say, unwholesome states, can't it be regarded as, well, let's say, wholesome aversion or unwholesome desire?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yes, if your meditation is right.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, as I said, if your meditation perpetuates the view of where the problem is when it isn't there,
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, it's not.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, it's just on account of desire, on account of wanting to be free from desire, unintentionally doing things that are increasing your desire.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why it matters what you do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not everything will free you from desire.
[SPEAKER_04]: But yes, everybody needs to want to have a desire to be free from these desires, because they're so unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: But how you go about it, that's now the difference.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, it's a...
[SPEAKER_03]: Not that, not that this, let's say, desire to get rid of, understand, but I think it's a problem, but the problem is the wrong approach.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, as I said, you know, when he doesn't welcome, he doesn't entertain, you know, you can go differently about those things, like thoughts of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: You could just, I don't know, think that, yeah, that's one way of getting rid of.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or you could, oh, I shall not open the door for this and they will leave.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's another way to get rid of.
[SPEAKER_04]: But they are mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_04]: You either have to open the door and get into a fight and try to deny it or chase it and exhaust yourself and abandon the gateway.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or you simply recognize, wait,
[SPEAKER_04]: As long as I don't open the door, they can't come in.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, they might shout and scream in front of the door, which is what I used to find unpleasant, which is why I open the door and try to calm my mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's not where the calmness was.
[SPEAKER_04]: The calmness was recognizing the gateway, protecting it.
[SPEAKER_04]: As the Buddha said, you find the city with only one entrance, one in and out, and you stand there.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you see who comes in and who not.
[SPEAKER_04]: In this case, in my simile, you don't open the door and they leave.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, either way, you haven't welcomed it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, there is a difference in the way a person would go about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's pretty much determining the intentions behind why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, you will know whether it's an immediate aversion of, I don't want this pain, or if it's like a broader picture, oh yeah, I am practicing towards freedom from desire, in that ultimate sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you develop the wisdom?
[SPEAKER_04]: Wisdom is not on the level of intellectual answers.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's on the level of being in control of your mind, not losing perspective.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's like the wise perspective.
[SPEAKER_04]: The person who is wise is the person who has perspective on things, who is not caught up in details of them.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, and you develop that by everything we've been describing.
[SPEAKER_07]: Do you have a name for the
[SPEAKER_07]: Things in the manner of... just like driving a boat.
[SPEAKER_07]: A boat has its path.
[SPEAKER_07]: This path is like emotion, okay?
[SPEAKER_07]: Now we are in the motion of joy or anger or something.
[SPEAKER_07]: This is a boat.
[SPEAKER_07]: And now someone can just turn the wheel and we go into another
[SPEAKER_04]: Like controlling emotions.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Certainly, in the Buddhist teaching, that's... that's not how emotions are described.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay?
[SPEAKER_04]: If you were to have a control over emotions, you wouldn't have been in a boat that goes in the direction of pain to begin with.
[SPEAKER_04]: That was the Buddha's point.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you might act out of emotions, and create new ones, and distract yourself with sensuality, but fundamentally, you are subjected to them first.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you were truly in control of them, you would never experience pain, because nobody wants pain.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if you're a master, means the pain would not be able to manifest itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the fact that it does manifest itself, even if you quickly evade it, means, well, yeah, but you are still subjected to emotions first.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is why they still come, when they want to come.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means, time will come when you will not be able to steer the boat to pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you want to recognize that before that time comes, like what we said.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the whole training.